Guide to the World War II Pamphlet Collection 1937-1991 (bulk 1939-1945)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
World War II pamphlet collection
1937-1991 (bulk 1939-1945)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Pam 02
10.0 linear feet
The World War II pamphlet collection contains approximately 1,000 pamphlets, magazines, booklets and book-length literature, and cartoons published during the Second World War or immediately thereafter.
This is a collection of materials directly related to and largely produced during World War II, or the Second World War. Included are official government publications and items from private organizations such as patriotic societies, socialist organizations, humanitarian associations and special interest groups. They represent a wide range of opinion from Belgian, German, Polish, English, Japanese, Norwegian, and Dutch sources.
This collection has been organized alphabetically by country of origin or subject and then chronologically when feasible. Although the grouping has been categorized and sorted at the folder level, item-level descriptive information has been drawn from records available in WorldCat.
Note that entries exist for the United Nations. This part of the collection contains information which was used to educate the American public about the purpose of the U.N. There are also many periodicals from special interest groups or government departments, most of them published in the United States.
Some of the periodicals were mailed directly to the University of Montana Kaimin newpaper, and others were mailed directly to the University of Montana’s then-president, George Finlay Simmons. Items of particular note include four pamphlets written in German and published in Great Britain. These pamphlets were part of Great Britain and America’s propaganda campaign against the German army. Other items of interest are “Make and Mend for Victory”, a book of Victory hat and clothing patterns; “News from Germany” cartoons satirizing Winston Churchill; and the “Japan-China Pictorial Primer”, in which Japan defends its military occupation of China.
Many of these materials cover a wide variety of information with no one categorization; they have been put under the most likely subheadings possible. Some of the periodicals are filed under a subject heading if they fit; otherwise, they are organized under the “News Coverage” heading. Atrocity literature has been grouped under the source country of the allegation rather than the subject country; e.g., atrocities alleged by Belgium against Germany would be found under Belgium. Other propaganda may be found under its source if the subject is primarily of national concern to the originating nation, such as a national issue like U.S.’s neutrality during the first part of the war which was of particular concern to Great Britain.
Because of the peculiar role played by the United States before its entry into the war, much of the English literature in this collection could be categorized as propaganda that was aimed at the U.S. In particular, most of the items published by the British Library of Information and British Information Services were expressly written for an American audience. Although much of this literature has been filed under “Propaganda: Aimed at the United States”, in some cases, certain pamphlets have been filed under other categories or subheadings to promote ease of searchability; e.g., pamphlets about the British Royal Air Force would be filed under “Military”.
Although India was a British colony during the war, the country has its own section because of the amount of literature on India. Also, pamphlets published by Serbians are located under Yugoslavia since Serbia did not become a nation until 2006.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The folder of German songs and stories filed under Germany - Military: Troop Morale was donated by Fred Skinner in 2009.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda
International Relations
- Austria - Propaganda: Against Germany (in English), 1942; Kostmann, Jenö. Restive Austria. London: Austrian Centre and Young Austria, 1942. (1/1)
- Australia - Propaganda, Patriotic (in English), 1941; Australia: A Monthly Bulletin from the Australian News and Information Bureau. New York: Australian news and information bureau, 1941. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box-folder 1/2)
- Australia - Propaganda, Patriotic (in English), 1942; Australia: A Monthly Bulletin from the Australian News and Information Bureau. New York: Australian news and information bureau, 1942. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box-folder 1/3)
- Belgium - German Occupation (in English), 1941-1942; Barzin, Betty. "We Suffer in a Thousand Ways": Letters from Occupied Belgium. New York: Belgian information center, 1942.; 10 Facts about Belgium Today. New York: the Center, 1941. (chiefly illustrated); They Ride through Belgium. New York, N.Y: Belgian Information Center, 1941. (Box 1/4)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium" (in English), 1941; News from Belgium. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1941. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 1/5)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium" (in English), 1942; News from Belgium. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1942. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 1/6)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium" (in English), 1942; News from Belgium. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1942. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 1/7)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1943; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1943. [(A serial publication; not all issues available.) ("News from Belgium" changed its title to "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" in 1943)] (Box 1/8)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1943; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1943. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 1/9)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1944; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1944. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 2/1)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1944; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1944. (A serial publication; not all issues available.); [Letter to All Friends of Belgium]. New York: Louvain Library Book Fund, Inc., 1944. (This letter was inserted in the October 21, 1994 issue of "News from Belgium" and is signed by Hugh Taylor, chairman of the Louvain Library Book Fund.) (Box 2/2)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1945; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1945. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 2/3)
- Belgium - German Occupation: "News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo" (in English), 1945; News from Belgium and the Belgian Congo. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1945. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 2/4)
- Belgium - Military: Campaigns/Battles (in English), 1941; Keyes, Roger. King Leopold Vindicated. New York: Belgian Information Office, 1941.; Rongé, Marcel A. "Fortissimi Sunt Belgae": The Heroism of the Belgian Army of 1940. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1941. (Box 2/5)
- Belgium - Military: Campaign, Congo (in English), 1941-1942; Weller, George. The Belgian Campaign in Ethiopia: A Trek of 2,500 Miles Through Jungle Swamps and Desert Wastes. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1941.; Belgian Congo at War. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1942 (Box 2/6)
- Belgium - Military: Personal Narratives (in English), 1941; Mueller, Merrill Escape from Belgium: The Story of Two Belgian Air Officers Who Escaped to England by Aeroplane. New York: Belgian Information Center, 1941. (Also titled "Flight for Freedom") (Box 2/7)
- Belgium - Propaganda, Patriotic (in English and French), 1942-1943; Belgium. New York: Belgian Press Association, 1942. (A serial publication; not all issues available.); Belgium. New York: Belgian Press Association, 1943. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 2/8)
- China - Atrocities Alleged: Against Japan (in English), 1938-1939; Japanese Aggression and the League of Nations 1939, VI. Geneva: Press Bureau of the Chinese Delegation, 1939.; Xu, Shuxi. The War Conduct of the Japanese. Shanghai: Kelly and Walsh, 1938. (Box 2/9)
- China - Reconstruction (in English), 1945; Contemporary China: A Reference Digest. New York: Chinese News Service, 1945. (A bi-weekly, serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 2/10)
- Czechoslovakia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in English), 1941; Hapsburgs and the Central European Federation. Chicago: Czechoslovak National Council of America, 1941. (Box 3/1)
- Czechoslovakia - Foreign Relations: with the United States (in English), undated; Zmrhal, Jaroslav J. Peace, Peace, but There Is No Peace, Address by Prof. J. J. Zmrhal,... Delivered on Czechoslovak Day at the World's Fair in New York City on July 28th, 1940. Chicago: Czechoslovak National Council of America, n.d. (Box 3/2)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation (in English), 1941; Munk, Frank. Slavery ... 1941 Model: A Discussion of the Methods Whereby the Conqueror of Today Imposes His Will on a Subject People. Chicago: Czechoslovak National Council of America, 1941. (Box 3/3)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1941; News from Czecho-Slovakia. New York: American Friends of Czecho-slovakia, 1941. (A bi-monthly, serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/4)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1941; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination. Chicago: The Council, 1941. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/5)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1942; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination. Chicago: The Council, 1942. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/6)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1943; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination. Chicago: The Council, 1943. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/7)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1944; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination. Chicago: The Council, 1944. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/8)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination" (in English), 1945; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia under Nazi Domination. Chicago: The Council, 1945. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 3/9)
- Czechoslovakia - German Occupation: "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia" (in English), 1946; News Flashes from Czechoslovakia. Chicago: The Council, 1946. [(A serial publication; not all issues available.) (The title changed to only "News Flashes from Czechoslovakia" since the war ended in 1945.)] (Box 3/10)
- France - Foreign Relations: with Great Britain (in English), 1940; Bernstein, Henri. Speech Broadcast by Monsieur Henri Bernstein. New York: British Library of Information, 1940. (Box 3/11)
- France - Propaganda, Patriotic (in English), 1940; Inside France: Excerpts from the French Press. New York: French News Service, 1940. (A weekly, serial publication; not all issues available.); Curie, Eve. Eve Curie Says French People Were Kept Ignorant of 'shame'. New York: New York Tribune, Inc., 1940. (Originally published in the "New York Herald Tribune", June 27, 1940.) (Box 3/12)
- Germany - Atrocities Alleged: Against Poland (in English and German), 1940; Schadewaldt, Hans. Polish Acts of Atrocity against the German Minority in Poland. Berlin: Volk und Reich Verlag, 1940. (Box 3/13)
- Germany - Foreign Relations: with Argentina (in German), 1944; Die Weite Welt. Berlin, 1944. (This tourist pamphlet discusses the the basic geography, demographics and culture of Argentina. Argentina's open-door immigration policy made it possible for many Nazis and Nazi collaborators to flee Europe and attempt to avoid punishment for war crimes.) (Box OS 19/1)
- Germany - Military: Troop Morale, 1938-1944 and undated (in German); Scheller, Thilo, Arthur Kastner, and Walter Kramer.; Standard-schlager: Die Schönsten U. Bekanntesten Liedertexte Der Jahre 1936-1938. (this is a long poem about the importance of physical fitness for young boys in the National Socialist regime) Berlin: Drei Masken Musik GmbH, 1939. (popular German songs between 1936 and 1938); Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. No. 101. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., 1938.; Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. Wirthaus. No. 102. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., 1938.; Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. Wirthaus. No. 103. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., 1938.; Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. Wirthaus. No. 110. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., 1939.; Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. Wirthaus. No. 112. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., n.d.; Die Neuesten Schlager und Liedertexte. Wirthaus. No. 113. Berlin: Drei Masken Musik G.m.b.H., 1939.; Es War Eine Raschende Ballnacht. Wittingen: Landsknecht-Presse, n.d. (part of the Die Prüfung: Erbauliche Verse Aus Dem Spandauer Leben series); Wegner, Max.Die Gebrochenen Hande. Stuttgart: Georg Truckenmüller, n.d.; Cysarz, Herbert, and Irmingard Ziegler-Dimitz. Mensch Und Geschichte. Feldpost. Weimar: Hermann Böhlau, 1943. (part of the Feldpost series); Eyth, Max.Der Blinde Passagier. Berlin: W. Kohlhammer Stuttgart, 1944. (No. 114 in the series Die Bunten Hefte fur Unsere Soldaten, which were little booklets of short stories printed for German troops); Baur, Ernst. Aus Der Vergangenheit: Zwei Erzählungen. Berlin: W. Kohlhammer Stuttgart, 1944. (No. 124 in the Die Bunten Hefte fur Unsere Soldaten series, which were little booklets of short stories printed for German troops) (3/14)
- Germany - Propaganda: Against Allied Nations (in English), undated; Pfaus, Oscar C. We Accuse!(press statement against Great Britain made in Chicago) (Box 3/15)
- Germany - Propaganda: Against Allied Nations (in English & German), 1940 and undated; Hoffman, H.R.? Cartoons: Supplement to "News from Germany". München?, 1940. [(Various caricatures of Winston Churchill and Paul Reynaud.) (This publication is referenced in the propaganda analysis "A Study of German Propaganda Being Spread in the United States" located in Box 18, Folder 3.)]; Kleine Geschichte mit grosser Moral (Little Story with a Big Moral). n.d. (Various caricatures of Winston Churchill and Great Britain.) (Box 3/16)
- Germany - Propaganda: Against Allied Nations (in English), 1940; Hoffmann, H.R. News from Germany. Starnberg: s.n., 1940. [(A serial publication; not all issues available.) (This publication is referenced in the propaganda analysis "A Study of German Propaganda Being Spread in the United States" which is located in Box 18, Folder 3.)] (Box 3/17)
- Germany - Propaganda: Against Allied Nations (in English), 1940; Hoffmann, H.R. American Views. Starnberg: s.n., 1940. (This serial publication is a supplement to "News from Germany.") (Box 4/1)
- Germany - Propaganda: Aimed at the United States (in English), 1940; German Library of Information: A Clearing House of Knowledge. New York: German library of information, 1940. (Box 4/2)
- Germany - Propaganda: Aimed at the United States (in English), 1940; Facts in Review. New York, N.Y: German Library of Information, 1940. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 4/3)
- Germany - Propaganda: Aimed at the United States (in English), 1941; Facts in Review. New York, N.Y: German Library of Information, 1941. (A serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 4/4)
- Germany - Patriotic Propaganda (in German), 1938; Weltkrieg 1914/18. Unseren Helden Zur Ehre! Fondermann and Co.: Haan bei Solingen, Rhld., 1938 (Box OS 19/7)
- Germany - Patriotic Propaganda (in German), 1938; Den Helden Zur Ehre! 1914/18 Kriegsflaggen. Fondermann and Co.: Haan bei Solingen, Rhld., 1938 (Box OS 19/7)
- Germany - Reconstruction: Soviet Occupation (in English), 1951; Confuse and Control: Soviet Techniques in Germany. Washington, D.C: Division of Publications, Office of Public Affairs, 1951. (Box 4/5)
- Great Britain - Colonialism (in English), 1940-1944 and undated; Do You Know? England, n.d.; What Is British Imperialism? New York: British Library of Information, 1940.; What is the British Empire? New York: British Library of Information, 1940. (This pamphlet was distributed at the British Pavilion of the New York World's Fair.); The British Commonwealth and Empire. New York: British Information Services, 1944. (Box 4/6)
- Great Britain - Colonialism: Africa (in English), 1944-1946; Introducing West Africa. New York: British Information Services, 1944.; Perham, Margery. African Facts and American Criticisms. New York: Council on Foreign Relations, 1944.; African Challenge: The Story of the British in Tropical Africa. New York, N.Y: British information services, 1945.; African Achievement, Building Tomorrow in British West Africa. New York, 1946. (Box 4/7)
- Great Britain - Colonialism: Ceylon [Sri Lanka] (in English), 1945; Mills, Lennox A. Britain and Ceylon. London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1945. (Box 4/8)
- Great Britain - Colonialism: Malaya [Malay Peninsula and Singapore] (in English), 1944; Winstedt, Richard. Britain and Malaya, 1786-1941. London, New York [etc.: Longmans, Green and Co., 1944. (Box 4/9)
- Great Britain - Colonialism: Middle East (in English), 1944; 50 Facts About the Middle East. New York City: British Information Services, 1944. (Box 4/10)
- Great Britain - Domestic Politics: Labor and Industry (in English), 1941-1944; Allen, G. C. British Industry [with plates]. London: Published for the British Council by Longmans & Co, 1944. (This book is No. 20 in a larger series titled, "British Life and Thought."); Bevin, Ernest. Labor's Achievements and the Goal. New York, N.Y: British Library of Information, 1941.; The British Farmer's Battle-and Victory. New York: Distributed by British information Services, 1944. (Box 4/11)
- Great Britain - Domestic Politics: War Effort (in English), 1944; Statistics Relating to the War Effort of the United Kingdom; Presented by the Prime Minister to Parliament by Command of His Majesty, November 1944. London: H.M.S.O, 1944. (Box 4/12)
- Great Britain - Foreign Politics: Trade (in English), 1940; Great Britain and the East. Incorporating " the Near East and India. " a Rewiew of the Affairs of Great Britain (including the British Empire), the Balkans, Turkey, Egypt, the Sudan, Malta, Cyprus, Palestine, Syria, Iraq, Iran, Arabia, Ethiopia, Afganistan, India, Fed. Malay States, China and Japan. London: "Great Britain & The East", 1940. (A weekly, serial publication; not all issues available.) (Box 4/13)
- Great Britain - Foreign Relations: with the Allies (in English), 1940; Our Lives, Our Fortunes, and Our Sacred Honour. New York: The British Library of Information, 1940. (Box 4/14)
- Great Britain - Foreign Relations: with Germany (in English and German), 1939-1941; The British War Blue Book: Miscellaneous No. 9 (1939) Documents Concerning German-Polish Relations and the Outbreak of Hostilities between Great Britain and Germany on September 3, 1939. London: H.M. Stationery Office, 1939.; Secret German Documents Seized During the Raid on the Lofoten Islands on the 4th March, 1941: Embodying Instructions to the Army on the Control of the Pres and on Collaboration with the Gestapo in Dealing with Norwegian Nationals. London: H.M. Stationery Office, 1941. (Box 4/15)
- Great Britain - Foreign Relations: with Russia (in English), 1943-1945; British Aid to Russia. New York City: British Information Services, 1943. (pictorial); Kekwick, James. Planned Reconstruction in the Soviet Union. London: Russia Today, 1945. (Box 4/16)
- Great Britain - Foreign Relations: with the United Nations (in English), 1946; 25 Facts About Britain and the United Nations. New York: British Information Services, 1946. (Box 4/17)
- Great Britain - Foreign Relations: with the United States (in English), 1940-1941; Wheeler-Bennett, John W. Britain Accepts the Challenge: Address Delivered Before the Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va. New York: British Library of Information, 1940.; Lothian, Philip H. K. Address by the Most Hon. the Marquess of Lothian, C.H., British Ambassador to the United States at Columbia University Commencement on June 4th, 1940. New York: British Library of Information, 1940.; Lothian, Philip H. K. Last Speech by the Marquess of Lothian, British Ambassador to the United States, 1939-1940 (died Dec. 12, 1940), Delivered to the American Farm Bureau Association, Baltimore, Md., Dec. 11, 1940. New York, N.Y: British Library of Information, 1940.; Halifax, Edward F. L. W. The Heritage of Freedom: Extracts from Speeches on Foreign Policy by Britain's New Ambassador to the United States. New York: British Library of Information, 1941.; Greene, Wilfrid A. Law and Liberty: An Address Delivered at Albany on the 28th of May 1941, on the Occasion of the 250th Anniversary of the Foundation of the Supreme Court of the State of New York. New York: British Library of Information, 1941.; Elizabeth,. Message to the Women of America: Broadcast by Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth, August 10, 1941. United Kingdom?: s.n, 1941. (2 copies); Roosevelt, Franklin D, Winston Churchill, and Bruce Rogers. The Atlantic Charter. New York: British Library of Information, 1941.; Correspondence Respecting the Policy of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom in Connexion with the Use of Materials Received Under the Lend-Lease Act, London, September 10, 1941. London: H.M. Stationery Office, 1941. (2 copies) (Box 4/18)
- Great Britain - Military: Air Force (in English), 1940-1944; Air Estimates: Statement by the Minister of Air in the House of Commons, Thursday, 7th March 1940. London: H.M. Stationery Office Press, 1940.; The Air Offensive against Germany. London?: British Information Service?, 1941. (This pictorial includes two maps.); R.A.F. New York: British Information Services, 1943. (pictorial); Flying Bombs. New York, N.Y: British information Services, 1944. [(2 copies) (pictorial)] (Box 4/19)
- Great Britain - Military: Army (in English), 1940; Stanley, Oliver F. G. Army Estimates: Statement by Mr. Oliver Stanley in the House of Commons on the 12th March, 1940. London: H.M. Stationery Office Press, 1940. (Box 4/20)
- Great Britain - Military: Campaign, Burma (in English), 1945; Victory in Burma. New York, N.Y: British Information Services, 1945. (pictorial with maps) (Box 4/21)